Inventory of the Kanzaki Kiichi papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Kanzaki Kiichi papers
circa 1913-1950
2017C49
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box (1.9 linear feet)
Diaries, speeches and writings relating to Japanese immigration to the United States, and to the Japanese community in the United States. Photocopies of archival documents held at Kwansei Gakuin University's Archives in Japan.
Kanzaki, Kiichi.
Location of Original Materials
Kansei Gakun Daigaku, Nishinomiya, Japan.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Kanzaki Kiichi was the general secretary of the Zaibei Nihonjinkai (Japanese Association of America) in San Francisco (1915-1921) and became the fifth president of Kwansei Gakuin University in Japan (1940-1950).
Scope and Content of Collection
The Kanzaki Kiichi papers include photocopies of the diaries of Kanzaki (1916, 1919, 1920, and 1921), his speech manuscripts on the Pacific and Japanese immigration issue in the United States, Japanese government studies on immigration issues, and U.S. court cases regarding Japanese citizenship and its related issues.
Japan--Emigration and immigration.; Japanese--United States.
- 移民調査報告 第11 (Imin chōsa hōkoku dai11), 外務省通商局 (Gaimushō tsūshōkyoku), 1913 January (Taisho 2) (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Immigration Study Report, Vol. 11, Ministery of Foreign Affairs of Japan. Two handwritten letters inserted. B5, 213 pp.
- 覚書 (棺村市民議案）) (Oboegaki (Sugimura? Shimin gian)), 桑港日本人会 棺村丈児 (Jōji Sugimura?), 1913? (Box 2)
  Memorandum (Sugimura United States citizenship proposal), Japanese Association of America, San Francisco. Inserted in "Imin chōsa hōkoku dai11." 5 sheets.
- Untitled, 1913? (Box 2)
- 日本移民協会横浜講習所概覧 (Nihon imin kyōkai Yokohama kōshūjo gairan), 日本移民協会 (Nihon imin kyōkai), 1916 June (Taisho 5) (Box 1)
  "Overview of Yokohama Training Center," Association of Japanese Immigration. A5, 15 pp.
- 渡米議員団報告書 (Tobei gi'indan hōkokusho), 1918 January (Taisho 7) (Box 1)
  Report of Diet delegates to the United States. A5, 38 pp.
- 米国西北部在留日本人発展略史 (Beikoku seihokubu zairyū Nihonjin hatten ryakushi), 連絡日本人会 (Renraku Nihonjinkai), 1921 October (Taisho 10) (Box 2)
  Summary history of Japanese residing in the Northwestern United States.
- 神崎驥一日記 (Kanzaki Kiichi nikki), 神崎驥一 (Kanzaki Kiichi) (Box 2)
  Kanzaki Kiichi diary.
  - 1916
  - 1919
  - 1920
    During his stay in the United States.
  - 1921
- 講演,論説,説話 草稿集 I (Box 1)
  Kanzaki's manuscripts for lectures, opinions, and essays.
  - 太平洋関係調査会議に於ける移民問題の考察 (Taiheiyō kankei chōsa kaigi ni okeru imin mondai no kōsatsu)
    Study on the immigration issue at Taiheiyo kanren chosa kaigi.
  - Untitled (49 sheets)
  - 就職難を嘆づる人々へ (Shūshoku nan o tanzuru hitobito e)
    "To those who lament on the difficult job market."
  - Untitled (6 sheets)
  - 生活に熱情を加へよ (Seikatsu ni netsujō o kuwaheyo)
    "Fuel your passion for your life."
  - 太平洋問題,将来ト米国西部諸州 (Taiheiyō mondai, shōrai ni kansuru ichi kōsatsu)
    The Pacific issue, the future, and the western states in the United States.
  - 米国の将来に対する一考察 (Beikoku no shōrai ni taisuru ikkō)
    "A study on the future of the United States."
- 講演,論説,説話 草稿集 II (Box 1)
  - 太平洋問題研究会議に関する私見 (Taiheiyō mondai kenkyū kaigi ni kansuru shiken)
    "My personal opinion on the Pacific issue."
  - 上記に関する講演要綱、会議報告など各種多数 (Jōki ni kansuru kōen yōkō, kaigi hōkoku nado kakushu tasū)
    Various materials on the Pacific issue, such as speech draft, meeting minutes
- 講演,論説,説話 草稿集 III (Box 1)
  - 対米移民問題は打切りか (Taibei imin mondai ha uchikirika), 1928 February 1 (Showa 3)
    Termination of the discussion on the United States immigration issue? Published in 外交時報 (Gaikō jihō).
  - Untitled (19 sheets)
    Intro missing.
  - 太平洋問題について (Taiheiyō mondai nitsuite)
    On the Pacific issue.
  - 戦後の欧州と其の将来 (Sengo to ōshū to sono shōrai)
    Post-war Europe and its future.
  - Untitled (36 sheets)
    Conclusion missing.
  - 加州邦人放逐の件 (Kashū hōjin hōchiku no ken)
    Concerning the Japanese banishment from California.
  - 基督教徒ト社会問題 (Kirisuto kyōto to shakai mondai)
    Christians and social issues.
  - Untitled (7 sheets)
  - 太平洋問題と其の基調 (Taiheiyō mondai to sono kichō)
    The Pacific issue and its baseline.
- "California and the Japanese," Kanzaki Kiichi, General Secretary of the Association of Japanese Residing in America (Box 2)
- 米国移民法上程に伴う理事会の報告書および関連書類 (Beikoku iminhō jōtei ni tomonau rijikai no hōkokusho oyobi kanrenshorui), 1924 (Box 1)
  Board report concerning the United States immigration laws and its related documents.
- Ichizo Sato v. Hall, 191 Cal. 510, Cal. Supreme Court (1923) (Box 2)
  Ichizo Sato vs. Harry W. Hall, Clerk of the County of Sacramento (Supreme Court of California). A Japanese soldier who served the United States Government during the late war and who has received an honorable discharge, entitled to citizenship under the Act of Congress of May 9th, 1918.
- The matter of the application of Heikichi Terui for a writ of habeas corpus (the Supreme Court of the State of California) (Box 2)
  A Japanese alien obligated to register and pay the poll tax as provided by the terms of the so-called alien poll tax of California.
- Takao Ozawa v. United States, 260 U.S. 178, U.S. Supreme Court (1922) (Box 2)
  Takao Ozawa vs. United States (No. 2888-2889, United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit)
- In re Terui, 187 Cal. 20, Cal. Supreme Court (1921) (Box 2)
  In the Matter of Heikichi Terui on Habeas Corpus (Crim. No. 2390, Supreme Court of California)
- In re Kotta, 187 Cal. 27, Cal. Supreme Court (1921) (Box 2)
  In the Matter of Guillermo D. Kotta on Habeas Corpus (Crim. No. 2394, Supreme Court of California)
- O’Brien v. Webb, 279 F. 117, Northern District of California (1921) (Box 2)
  O'Brien et al. v. Webb, Attorney General of California, et al. (No. 654, United States District Court for the Northern District of California)